Guide to the Czesław Miłosz Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1934-2000; Series II; 30.44; (74 boxes)
  - Prose
    - Essays and Other Shorter Works of Prose
      - English
        - Untitled and Unidentified Works
          - "How to penetrate what is going on in the minds of our contemporaries ..." (on religion and society), draft, holograph, corrected, undated (Box 126, Folder 1995)
          - "In the last few years ..." (on Kazimierz Brandys), draft, typescript, undated, after 1981 (Box 126, Folder 1996)
          - "In this extraordinary year rich in political hope ..." (on the notion of Central Europe), holograph, undated, after 1981 (Box 126, Folder 1997)
          - "In winter 1945/46 a small Britsh cargo ship brought me and my wife...," draft, holograph, corrected, undated (Box 126, Folder 1998)
          - "It is too early to give a picture...," draft, holograph, corrected, undated (Box 126, Folder 1999)
          - "Perhaps I am entitled to add something to the present discussions on Lithuania ...," draft, holograph, corrected, undated, after 1989 (Box 126, Folder 2000)
          - "Questions of nationality and patriotism" (on linguistic nationalism), holograph and printout, undated (Box 126, Folder 2001)
          - "To introduce Oskar Vladislas de Lubicz Milosz ...," copy of typescript, undated (Box 126, Folder 2002)
          - Various titles, photocopies made by the Beinecke Library for Miłosz, undated (Box 126, Folder 2003-2004)
          - Unidentified fragments and notes, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 126, Folder 2005-2011)
      - French
        - "Adam Mickiewicz: Entre les monuments et l'oubli," draft, typescript, 1955 (Box 127, Folder 2012)
        - "L'amour absolu," draft, typescript carbon and printed version, circa 1956 (Box 127, Folder 2013)
          Alternate title: "L'amour impossible"
        - "Au 'coeur des ténèbres' du XIXe siècle: Le Père de Joseph Conrad," draft, typescript, corrected, 1956 (Box 127, Folder 2014)
          Translated by André Prudhommeaux.
        - "Au sujet de l'insurection de Varsovie" (letter to the editor of Esprit ), draft, typescript, corrected, 1952 (Box 127, Folder 2015)
        - "Bieliński et la licorne," draft, typescript, corrected, circa 1955 (Box 127, Folder 2016)
          For an English language version, see "Bieliński and the unicorn"
        - Les Confins de l'ancienne Pologne, edited by Daniel Beauvois (preface by Miłosz), draft, typescript, corrected and printed version, 1988 (Box 127, Folder 2017)
        - "Deux procès de sorcellerie: Prague et Afrique Occidentale Française," drafts, handwritten by Jeanne Hersch and typescript carbon, 1953 (Box 127, Folder 2018)
          For an English language version, see the lecture "Two trials of witchcraft -- Africa and Prague."
        - "Un dimanche à Brunnen," draft, typescript carbon, corrected, 1954 (Box 127, Folder 2019)
        - Ernest Rutherford: Atom pioneer, by John Rowland (review by Miłosz), draft, typescript, 1950s (Box 127, Folder 2020)
        - Goldsborough, by Stefan Heym (review by Miłosz), draft, typescript, 1950s (Box 127, Folder 2021)
        - "La grande peur des intellectuels," drafts, handwritten by Jeanne Hersch and typescript, corrected, 1952 (Box 127, Folder 2022)
        - "La grande tentation," printed version, 1951? (Box 127, Folder 2023)
        - "L'interlocuteur fraternel," copy of 1960 printed version, undated (Box 127, Folder 2024)
        - "Le mémoire de Bel," drafts, typescript, corrected and typescript carbon, 1950s (Box 127, Folder 2025)
        - "Littérature en Pologne," draft, typescript carbon, corrected, 1950s (Box 127, Folder 2026)
        - "Oscar Milosz et William Blake," drafts, holograph and copy of typescript, corrected, printed version and copies of printed version, 1977 (Box 127, Folder 2027-2028)
        - "En pleine lueur," printed version, 1980s (Box 127, Folder 2029)
          Excerpt from Ziema Ulro, translated by Konstanty Jeleński.
        - "La poésie de l'Ouest et de l'Est," drafts, holograph, typescript and copy of typescript, corrected, undated (Box 127, Folder 2030)
        - "Pologne, enfant terrible," draft, typescript carbon, corrected, 1950s (Box 127, Folder 2031)
        - "Pologne: La pyramide détruite," draft, typescript, 1956 (Box 127, Folder 2032)
        - "Premières impressions de la guerre civile," draft, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 127, Folder 2033)
        - "Quelques problèmes personnels," draft, typescript, corrected, 1950s (Box 127, Folder 2034)
        - "Rencontres," draft, typescript, 1958 (Box 127, Folder 2035)
          Translated from Polish ("Spotkanie") by Jeanne Hersch.
        - So many hungers, by Bhabani Bhattacharya (review), draft, typescript carbon, 1950s (Box 127, Folder 2036)
        - "Les Tambours de la Tribu," draft, typescript carbon, corrected, 1950s (Box 127, Folder 2037)
        - "Vakla, ou hors du temps," draft, typescript carbon, corrected, 1955 (Box 127, Folder 2038)
          Alternate title "Le camp de Valka."
        - Untitled and unidentified works
          - (On Samuel Beckett), draft, holograph, corrected, after 1952 (Box 127, Folder 2039)
          - "Il est à demander s'il n'y a pa de coquetterie dans le mot 'angoise' ...," draft, holograph, circa 1953 (Box 127, Folder 2040)
          - "Il est évident qu'il faut écrire sur le communisme ...," draft, holograph, circa 1954 (Box 127, Folder 2041)
          - "Face aux événements de Poznan ...," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, circa 1956 (Box 127, Folder 2042)
          - "On exagère d'ordinaire...," holograph, corrected, circa 1956 (Box 127, Folder 2043)
          - " Misère des intellectuels français de Dionys Mascolo...," holograph, corrected, circa 1957 (Box 127, Folder 2044)
          - "Ce choix de textes n'aura sans doute ..." (on Simone Weil), typescript carbon, circa 1958 (Box 127, Folder 2045)
          - "Dans une autre enquête ...," holograph, corrected, 1950s (Box 127, Folder 2046)
          - "Je cite Mailer 'To swing'...," holograph, corrected, 1950s (Box 127, Folder 2047)
          - "Le oeuvre d'Albert Camus est théologique...," draft, typescript, corrected, 1960 (Box 127, Folder 2048)
          - "C'est que le nationalisme aujourd'hui ...," typescript carbon, circa 1960 (Box 127, Folder 2049)
          - "Ma première visite ..." (on Oscar V. de L. Milosz), draft, holograph, corrected, 1987 (Box 127, Folder 2050)
          - "J'appartiens à ceux qui doivent ..." (on Jeanne Hersch), drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, 2000 (Box 127, Folder 2051)
          - Unidentified fragment, holograph, 1953 (Box 127, Folder 2052)
      - German
        - "Polische Literatur bis 1945," draft, typescript, corrected, 1950s (Box 127, Folder 2053)
        - Untitled, "Eine Landkarte Europas ...," draft, typescript, circa 1952 (Box 127, Folder 2054)
  - Notebooks
    Folder descriptions in quotation marks are derived from labels Miłosz wrote on the notebooks.
    - "1934 rok studia", circa 1934 (Box 128, Folder 2055)
      Includes the poems Ogród Arsenału (printed as Bramy Arsenału ), "Ty silna noc…," the short story "Trzydziesta dziewiąta zima w życiu Leny…", fragments of prose, drama and notes in Polish and French.
    - "1", 1956-1960 (Box 128, Folder 2056)
      Includes poems, many later printed in the volume Król Popiel i inne wiersze. Drafts and clean copies, some corrected.
    - "Prywatne" (I-III), 1961-1973 (Box 128, Folder 2057-2059)
      Includes poems, many later printed in the volumes Król Popiel i inne wiersze, Gucio zaczarowany, Miasto bez imienia, Gdzie wschodzi słońce i kędy zapada. Drafts and clean copies, some corrected.
    - "Notatki" (hard-bound notebook), 1966 (Box 128, Folder 2060)
      Includes short notes published in Kultura 1966(5-6). Drafts and clean copies, some corrected.
    - "Materiały" (I, III, IV, V, V), 1953-1970s (Box 128, Folder 2061-2065)
      Five notebooks are labeled "Materiały" (1953-1970s). There is no notebook labeled "Materiały II" and two notebooks are labeled "Materiały V."
      Includes bibliographies, notes and excerpts from readings. "Materiały V" includes notes for learning Greek.
    - On Fyodor Dostoyevsky, 1972-1973 (Box 129, Folder 2066-2070)
    - Notebook, red, 1980s (Box 129, Folder 2071)
      Includes English and French autotranslations of poems: "Na pożegnanie mojej żony Janiny," "Tytanic," and notes on Aleksander Wat's Mediterranean Poems.
    - Notebook, red, spiral bound, 1980 (Box 129, Folder 2072)
      Includes English autotranslations of poems: "In Warsaw," "A Legend," "Earth," "Reflections," "In Milano," "Roki," "Felicja," "Chagrin," "When after a long life," "Early morning," "Secretaries," "Step back from me," "Flight," "When I was telling," "Metaphysical Pause," "Siegfried and Erika," "1945," and "Fear-Dream 1918."
    - Notebook, red, spiral bound, 1987 (Box 130, Folder 2073)
      Includes drafts of autotranslations from Polish to English for The Collected Poems 1931-1987, a review of the work of Norman Davies and other unidentified writings.
    - Notebook, pink, spiral bound, circa 1987 (Box 130, Folder 2074)
      Drafts of English translations for The Collected Poems 1931-1987.
    - Notebook, blue, spiral bound, 1987 (Box 130, Folder 2075)
      Includes notes for a colloquium at Lille (France) and drafts of essays on Judaism in Poland, on Zygmunt Hertz, and on Abraham Brumberg.
    - Notebook, yellow, spiral bound, 1987-1988 (Box 130, Folder 2076)
      Includes drafts of autotranslations from Polish to English of various poems, draft of a text in English on nationalism, draft of the preface for The Collected Poems 1931-1987, and drafts of letters to François Mitterand and Elie Wiesel.
    - Letter pad, circa 1988 (Box 130, Folder 2077)
      Includes a draft in English of the essay "On Exile" (introduction to Exiles by Josef Kudelka) and translation from English to Polish of three poems from The Baltic elegies by Ivar Ivask.
    - Letter pad, circa 1990 (Box 130, Folder 2078)
      Includes a draft of a translation from Lithuanian to Polish of Tautiška Giesme, the national anthem of Lithuania.
    - Letter pad, circa 1990 (Box 130, Folder 2079)
      Includes corrections to the first edition of Rok myśliwego.
    - Letter pad, 1990s (Box 130, Folder 2080)
    - Letter pad, 1990s (Box 130, Folder 2081)
      Następca (Inheritor), autotranslation to English, draft.
    - Letter pad, 1990s (Box 130, Folder 2082)
      Includes list of poems by Anna Świrszczyńska and Zbigniew Herbert and an essay on Paweł Mayewski.
    - Letter pad, 1990s (Box 130, Folder 2083)
      Lists of poems and English translation of Far Away.
    - Letter pad, 1990s (Box 130, Folder 2084)
      Includes various notes and translation from French to Polish of the Aloysius Bertrand's poem Le Maçon ( Murarz )
    - Loose pages, 1990s (Box 130, Folder 2085)
      Includes lists for the anthology A Book of Luminous Things.
    - Letter pad, 1990s (Box 130, Folder 2086)
      Includes translation from French to English of Jean Follain's poem Mirror and the essay "Outlines of a thought."
    - Letter pads, 1990s (Box 131, Folder 2087-2093)
      Includes English translations of the poems from the volume Dalsze okolice ( Provinces ), English translations of Zbigniew Machej's poems and drafts of unidentified prose writings.
    - Loose pages, 1990s (Box 131, Folder 2094)
      Includes notes for Rok myśliwego and translation from Polish to English of the poem Portret z kotem ( A Portrait with a Cat ).
    - Letter pad, 1990s (Box 131, Folder 2095)
      Includes English translation of the poem Literatura polska ( On Polish literature ) and notes on Anna Świrszczyńska.
    - Letter pads, circa 1991 (Box 131, Folder 2096-2097)
      Partial draft of the essay "Czy będzie powieść?"
    - Letter pad, circa 1993 (Box 131, Folder 2098)
      Includes notes on Tobie Wilno and other books, and notes for the anthology A Book of Luminous Things.
    - Letter pad, circa 1995 (Box 131, Folder 2099)
      Includes the texts "A laureate" and "Wstęp do Aušry," English translations of the poems from the volume Dalsze okolice ( Provinces ) and notes for the anthology A Book of Luminous Things.
    - Letter pad, circa 1997 (Box 131, Folder 2100)
      Notes in Polish and English and corrections for the second edition of Abecadło Miłosza.
    - Miscellaneous notes, 1965-1979, undated (Box 131, Folder 2101-2105)
  - Translations by Miłosz
    Organized under two headings: Into Polish and Into English.
    Unless otherwise indicated, files consist of typescript or holograph drafts, many corrected.
    - Into Polish
      Arranged alphabetically by author, file title or title of printed work.
      - Aiken, Conrad, undated (Box 132, Folder 2106)
      - Andrade, Jorge Carrera, 1947 (Box 132, Folder 2107)
      - Antoninus, Brother
        See: Everson, William
      - Baudelaire, Charles, 1936 (Box 132, Folder 2108)
      - Bell, Daniel Work and its Discontents / Praca i jej gorycze, 1957 (Box 132, Folder 2109-2110)
      - Biblia (The Bible)
        - Notebooks
          - Notes for learning Hebrew, 1970s (Box 132, Folder 2111)
          - Ewangelia według Marka (1-5), 1970s (Box 132, Folder 2112)
          - Ewangelia według Marka (5-12), 1970s (Box 132, Folder 2113)
          - Ewangelia według Marka (12-16), Księga Mądrości (1-7), 1970s (Box 132, Folder 2114)
          - Księga Mądrości (7-14), 1970s (Box 132, Folder 2115)
          - Księga Mądrości (14-19), 1970s (Box 132, Folder 2116)
          - Księga Psalmów (1-39), circa 1974 (Box 132, Folder 2117-2118)
            Includes a clean copy of the poem Lauda and parts of the Puławski Psalter copied by Miłosz.
          - Księga Psalmów (26-150), circa 1974 (Box 133, Folder 2119-2123)
            Includes parts of the Puławski Psalter copied by Miłosz.
          - Księga Psalmów (1-136), 1970s (Box 133, Folder 2124-2128)
          - Księga Psalmów (137-150) and Księga Hioba (1-10), 1970s (Box 134, Folder 2129)
          - Księga Hioba (10-27), 1970s (Box 134, Folder 2130)
          - Księga Hioba (27-40), 1970s (Box 134, Folder 2131)
          - Księga Hioba (40-42), revisions of Księga Psalmów, 1970s (Box 134, Folder 2132)
          - Księgi Pięciu Megilot, 1970s (Box 134, Folder 2133)
          - Apokalipsa, 1970s (Box 134, Folder 2134-2135)
        - Drafts, loose pages, holograph and typescript
          - Księga Psalmów, 1979 (Box 134, Folder 2136-2137)
          - Księga Psalmów, 1979 (Box 135, Folder 2138-2141)
            Includes a photocopy of a translation by Jan Szeruda.
          - Księga Hioba, 1979-1980 (Box 135, Folder 2142-2144)
          - Pieśń nad Pieśniami and Treny, 1970s (Box 135, Folder 2145)
          - Księga Ruth, 1970s (Box 135, Folder 2146)
          - Eklezjasta, 1970s (Box 135, Folder 2147-2148)
          - Księga Estery, 1970s (Box 135, Folder 2149)
          - Księga Mądrości, 1970s (Box 136, Folder 2150-2151)
          - Ewangelia według Marka, 1970s (Box 136, Folder 2152)
          - Apokalipsa, 1970s (Box 136, Folder 2153)
          - Introduction and commentaries, 1980s (Box 136, Folder 2154-2161)
          - Introduction and commentaries, 1980s (Box 137, Folder 2162-2163)
          - Notes, 1970s (Box 137, Folder 2164)
      - "Black Poets", 1940s (Box 137, Folder 2165)
        Includes translations of poetry by Nicholas Guillen, H.D. Carberry, Helene Johnson and Owen Dodson.
      - Blake, William, 1974, undated (Box 137, Folder 2166-2167)
      - Bomze, Nuchim, 1955 (Box 137, Folder 2168)
      - Browning, Robert, 1945, undated (Box 137, Folder 2169)
      - Burns, Robert, 1945 (Box 137, Folder 2170)
      - Cavafy, Constantine, 1960s (Box 137, Folder 2171)
      - Clay, Cassius Marcellus, 1948 (Box 137, Folder 2172)
        Memoir, one-page excerpt
      - Czas niepokoju: antologia współczesnej poezji brytyjskiej i amerykańskiej, edited by Paveł Mayewski, 1957 (Box 137, Folder 2173)
      - Eliot, T.S., 1943-1949 (Box 137, Folder 2174)
      - Everson, William, undated (Box 137, Folder 2175)
      - Faulkner, William, undated (Box 137, Folder 2176)
      - Garcia Lorca, Federico, 1948, undated (Box 137, Folder 2177-2178)
      - Gibbon, Edward, Decline and fall of the Roman Empire, one-page excerpt, 1948 (Box 138, Folder 2179)
      - Ginsberg, Allen, undated (Box 138, Folder 2180)
        "Howl," fragment
      - Haiku
        - Introduction, draft, holograph, circa 1992 (Box 138, Folder 2181)
        - Drafts, typescript and correspondence, 1992 (Box 138, Folder 2182-2184)
      - I Ching, drafts and galley proofs, 1949, undated (Box 138, Folder 2185-2186)
      - Jeffers, Robinson, 1960s (Box 138, Folder 2187-2188)
      - Keats, John, 1945 (Box 138, Folder 2189)
      - Kultura masowa
        - Introduction, draft, holograph, corrected, 1959 (Box 138, Folder 2190)
        - "Dobro-zła dziewczyna," draft, holograph, corrected, 1950s (Box 138, Folder 2191)
          Translation of "The good-bad girl," by Martha Wolfensetein and Nathan Leites
      - Lawrence, D.H., 1983 (Box 138, Folder 2192)
      - Lindsay, Vachel, undated (Box 138, Folder 2193)
      - Maimon, Solomon, undated (Box 138, Folder 2194)
        Autobiography, first chapter
      - Merkham, Edwin, undated (Box 138, Folder 2195)
        "Człowiek z motyką"
      - Merton, Thomas
        - "Elegia dla Ernesta Hemingwaya," draft, holograph, undated (Box 138, Folder 2196)
        - "List do niewinnego świadka," draft, holograph, circa 1959 (Box 138, Folder 2197)
      - Milosz, Oscar V. de Lubicz, Storge and other poems, 1993, undated (Box 138, Folder 2198-2202)
      - Milton, John, 1945-1954 (Box 139, Folder 2203)
      - Mowa wiązana, 1983-1984, undated (Box 139, Folder 2204-2212)
      - "Negro Spirituals", 1948 (Box 139, Folder 2213-2214)
      - Neruda, Pablo, poems, undated (Box 140, Folder 2215-2216)
      - Pereda Valdés, Ildefonso, undated (Box 140, Folder 2217)
        "Kołysanka dla murzyńskiego dziecka" and "Rynek na wyspie Trinidad"
      - [Pien, Chi Lin?], undated (Box 140, Folder 2218)
      - Rannit, Aleksis, undated (Box 140, Folder 2219)
      - "Rybki" (short Yiddish poems), undated (Box 140, Folder 2220)
      - Sandburg, Carl, undated (Box 140, Folder 2221)
      - Seymour, A.J., undated (Box 140, Folder 2222)
        "Ponad Gujaną Chmury"
      - Shakespeare, William
        - Othello, drafts and copy of 1950 printed version, circa 1950 (Box 140, Folder 2223-2227)
          Includes a contract with Państwowy Instytut Wydawniczy.
        - Jak wam się podoba ( As you like it ), drafts, 1945 (Box 140, Folder 2228-2231)
        - Jak wam się podoba ( As you like it ), proof and correspondence with publishers, 1945-1951 (Box 141, Folder 2232-2236)
      - Sherrard, Philip, "Oscar Milosz and the Vision of the Cosmos", circa 1986 (Box 141, Folder 2237-2238)
      - Stevens, Wallace, undated (Box 141, Folder 2239)
        "Wiersz, który stanął zamiast góry"
      - Supervielle, Jules, undated (Box 141, Folder 2240)
        "Modlitwa do nieznanego"
      - Traherne, Thomas, undated (Box 141, Folder 2241-2242)
        Z "Poematów szczęśliwości"
      - Weil, Simone, Wybór pism (compiled and translated by Miłosz)
        - "Wyznania tłumacza," draft, holograph, corrected, 1958 (Box 141, Folder 2243)
        - Introduction, drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, circa 1991 (Box 141, Folder 2244)
      - Whitman, Walt, 1978?, undated (Box 141, Folder 2245)
        "Szedłem o poranku," "Do lokomotywy w zimie," "Dziecko zapytało," "Kiedy z oceanem," "Pieśni dla poległych," "Słyszałem was uroczyście i słodko brzmiące organy," "Noc na preriach," "Opowiedziała mi to," "Miasto uczt," "Łzy! łzy! łzy!," and "Dzieci Adama."
      - Unidentified, undated (Box 141, Folder 2246-2248)
      - Anthology of poetry translations, 1948 (Box 141, Folder 2249)
      - Anthology of English and American poetry, notes, 1945 (Box 141, Folder 2250)
      - Anthology of English and American poetry, drafts and table of contents, 1945 (Box 142, Folder 2251-2253)
    - Into English
      Material consists of typescript or holograph drafts, unless otherwise indicated.
      Autotranslations of Miłosz's own poems are filed in the Verse subseries.
      - Barańczak, Stanisław, 1979 (Box 143, Folder 2254)
      - Białoszewski, Miron, 1957-1958 (Box 143, Folder 2255)
      - Czechowicz, Jozef, undated (Box 143, Folder 2256)
        "Through Remote Provinces," "Preludium" and "A Village Dream"
      - Grochowiak, Stanisław, undated (Box 143, Folder 2257)
        "Gladiators nani," "A Short Fairy-tale," "To a Lady," "XXX," "The Village Cinema," "The Village Moviehouse," "The Lion" and "Landscape."
      - Harasymowicz, Jerzy, undated (Box 143, Folder 2258)
        "The linden tree," "Sister," "Outskirts of a town," "Leda with a swan".
      - Herbert, Zbigniew, undated (Box 143, Folder 2259)
        Includes "Report from a besieged city," typescript, corrected
      - Iwaszkiewicz, Jarosław, undated (Box 143, Folder 2260)
        "To my wife," "Breughel," "Valse triste" and "Quintin Matsys."
      - Jastrun, Mieczysław, undated (Box 143, Folder 2261)
        "A beginning"
      - Kabir, undated (Box 143, Folder 2262)
      - Lechoń, Jan, undated (Box 143, Folder 2263)
        "Preludium"
      - Leśmian, Bolesław, undated (Box 143, Folder 2264)
        "A graveyard," "Memories," "Ballad of...," and "God, so glorious in the sky..."
      - Mickiewicz, Adam, undated (Box 143, Folder 2265)
      - Milosz, Oscar V. de Lubicz
        - The Arcana, drafts, holograph, corrected, undated (Box 143, Folder 2266-2270)
        - The Arcana, draft, typescript (copy), undated (Box 144, Folder 2271)
        - Ars Magna, undated (Box 144, Folder 2272-2275)
        - The Noble Traveller, (translator's introductory notes), draft, typesript, corrected, 1984 (Box 144, Folder 2276-2277)
        - "Quelques mots sur la poesie,", undated (Box 144, Folder 2278)
      - Norwid, Cyprian K., undated (Box 144, Folder 2279)
        "To citizen John Brown," "A Trifle," "The first letter which came to me," "The Slav," "A mournful Rhapsody in Bem's memory," "A Song about our land," "An Answer to Italy," "Tenderness," "Epos - of Ours," "Not you I invoke Apollo."
      - Postwar Polish Poetry
        - [Preface to the 1968 Penguin edition?] ( Polish post-war poetry ), copy of printed version (Box 144, Folder 2280)
        - Draft (fragment), holograph and typescript, 1981 (Box 144, Folder 2281)
        - Setting copy, 1983 (Box 144, Folder 2282)
      - Przyboś, Julian, undated (Box 145, Folder 2283)
        "Equation of the Heart" and "Spring 1942"
      - Rolicz-Lieder, Wacław (Box 145, Folder 2284)
        "I am a Satyr," "To the same / Stefan George / sending a wafer," "A Prayer for Organ," "Nocturnal Bells" and "A Ballad on Juliusz Zeyer."
      - Różewicz, Tadeusz, 1948, undated (Box 145, Folder 2285-2286)
        "A Rose," "Purification," "Lamentation," "The White of an Egg," "We are moving," "The Color of Eyes and Questions," "A Little House," "You know who I am?," "A Dithyramb in Honor of the Mother-in-Law," "But whoever sees," and "The Crystal Inside of a Dirty Man."
      - Rymkiewicz, Jarosław Marek, undated (Box 145, Folder 2287)
        "On the death of Christian Dior" and "New Atlantis."
      - Sihanouk, Norodom, "What will be our fate after Vietnam?", 1968 (Box 145, Folder 2288)
      - Słonimski, Antoni, undated (Box 145, Folder 2289)
        "A Document of the Epoch," "Rome," "O my artist," "To a son of my friends," "A scent," "Legacy," "The Codicil," "Hell and Heaven," "Words," "A conversation," "Last will and testament."
      - Słowacki, Juliusz, letters, undated (Box 145, Folder 2290)
      - Staff, Leopold, undated (Box 145, Folder 2291)
        "Duckweed," "Foundations," and "The Bridge"
      - Swir, Anna